<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hack | Bede Engineering]]></title>
  <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/categories/hack/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-24T16:55:39+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://engineering.bedegaming.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bede Gaming Ltd]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bede Gaming Sponsors Biggest Hackathon in the North East]]></title>
    <link href="http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/11/13/bede-sponsors-hackne/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-13T09:20:08+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://engineering.bedegaming.com/blog/2014/11/13/bede-sponsors-hackne</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Billed as <a href="http://http://www.chroniclelive.co.uk/news/local-news/newcastle-set-north-easts-biggest-8052017">“The biggest public hackathon ever held in the North East”</a>, <a href="http://hackne.com">Hack NE</a>, for Bede, was an ideal opportunity to get our name known in the community.  With a largely student based attendee list, people had come from as far away as London to compete. With free t-shirts, face cloths, breath mints, wet wipes and swag bags, Bede&rsquo;s branded 8Gig USB sticks looked a good addition for those brave enough to come talk to us.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As co-sponsor, we set a challenge for the competing teams. Bede supplied a Kafka service to publish a real-time event stream of messages about deposits, withdrawals and winners for a mock gaming website. We challenged the Hackers to consume the messages and create something beautiful.</p>

<h3>Day 1, 9AM</h3>

<p>With the hackers seated in the halls of the Hancock museum, and ready to start, Bede MD Dan Smyth took to the podium to deliver an inspired speech about Bede and an introduction to our challenge. This was followed by 5 other sponsors. All told there were 5 prizes on offer, including the actual Hack NE overall champion.</p>

<p>Representing the tech side of Bede were: Mark Radford, Daniel Lackenby, Amila Prabandhika, Richard Thompson and Anton Jidkov, with Andy Thompson fielding questions about the company and careers opportunities. As the teams started work on whose services they would use, a few nervous hackers approached us and asked for more details on the service. It seemed that with a prize of £100 Amazon vouchers per team member, we had their interest.</p>

<p>By the time the Bede techies had retired for the day, three teams of hackers had incorporated our challenge into their projects, using Java and Ruby Kafka clients respectively to consume the data we had made available. Just from walking around the room and assisting where we could to get teams up and running with the data there was no question that some cool hacks were being undertaken using Bede’s service as well as teams that had gone for their own ideas. We left them to their night of caffeine and code.</p>

<h3>Day 2, 7AM</h3>

<p>The room of hackers had been whittled down to a hardy few, breakfast was being served.
A slight panic had arisen at 3am, the Kafka service has stopped responding to requests…
A restart of the service had it working again so all was not lost for the teams that had pushed through.
Bede USB Sticks all gone, loads of SendGrid T-shirts left.</p>

<h3>Day 2 9AM</h3>

<p>Presentations were to be done in the Newcastle Students Union.
In total, 8 teams presented with 6 having a finished, working product.
Each sponsor gets to award their prize to the team they liked best with the overall prize being awarded by MLH.
The best presentations were:
Stockcruiser - a fantastic visual representation of organically created cars that ran along a track. The track was generated by using data from the Bloomberg API with the car jumping based on Bede&rsquo;s winners feed and power ups appearing with deposits.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hack-stockcruiser.jpg" title="&lsquo;Stock Cruiser Presentation&rsquo; &lsquo;Stock Cruiser Presentation&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Metro Apologises - Using the Metro information boards as a theme, they showed the Winners there and took the Bloomberg stocks figures to show a cartoon metro train derailing itself (or other reactions depending on the size of the figures).
BloomBedeGridMachine - Using an Arduino board and an LED Ticker Grid, The Bede winners ticked across the Grid and then showed a graph of the winning amounts over a time period. Then, a click of a remote control and the Feed showed Stock prices from the Bloomberg API.
<img class="center" src="/images/hack-crablab.jpg" title="&lsquo;Crablab present BloomBedeGridMachine&rsquo; &lsquo;Crablab present BloomBedeGridMachine&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>A quick conflab with the other sponsors and we each decided our winners. Bede awarded its prize to the BloomBedeGridMachine.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/hack-handshake.jpg" title="&lsquo;Bede Congratulate the Winners&rsquo; &lsquo;Bede Congratulate the Winners&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>Despite presenting on a refreshments trolley, they had worked extremely well as a team, each taking a single task on with one team member linking all the parts together and project managing.
One team member is quoted as saying “That Kafka software is awful to integrate with”.</p>

<p>We had a lot of enquires about Bede as a prospective employer and if we take summer/year long interns. All in all, Bede has projected a positive message to the local tech community and looks forward to hosting more hackathons in the future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
